Finding Aid for the Inesita Papers LSC.2365
UCLA Library Special Collections
Inesita papers
1913-2018
UCLA Library Special Collections
Inesita
LSC.2365
7 linear feet (12 boxes, 3 flat boxes, 1 carton)
18.92 Gigabytes (11 digital files)
Inesita (1921-) is a Los Angeles-based dancer whose work and oeuvre is devoted to traditional forms of Spanish dance, including flamenco, the Bolero School of Dance of the 18th century, and other regional dances of Spain. Since the age of fourteen, she has performed in cabaret; film; television; musical theater; and as a soloist since the early 1950s in venues throughout Los Angeles, San Francisco, New York City, Mexico City, Madrid, Paris, London, Liverpool, and Valletta. The papers are a reflection of an eight decade career and include business and personal correspondence, contracts, programs, posters, press clippings, photographs, scripts, notes, ephemera, memorabilia, and a manuscript of Inesita's autobiography A Dancer's Life. The collection also contains digital and audiovisual materials, which include various audio and video recordings of performances or fragments of dance shows.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS PROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment will be required for viewing. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Inesita, 2018.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9989156753606533
Biographical / Historical
Anice Mignon (née Stahl) Dworkin, best known as Inesita, was born on July 11, 1921 in New York City to parents who were classically trained musicians. She first studied violin and piano at an early age. Inesita's career as a Spanish dance artist began at the age of fourteen, not long after moving to Los Angeles, CA. Her work is devoted to traditional forms of Spanish dance, including flamenco, the Bolero School of Dance of the 18th century, and the regional dances of Spain's autonomous communities. Her studies began in Los Angeles and Mexico with Michael Brigante, Jose Fernandez, Janet Riesenfeld, Oscar Tarriba, and Antonio Triana; and then inevitably in Spain where she trained under the flamenco masters, Valencia y Rendón de Ávila ("El Estampio") and Regla Ortega, as well as the Pericet Family of la escuela bolera in Madrid. Since her first show at La Golondrina Café on Olvera Street on October 7th, 1939, Inesita has performed in cabaret, film, television, and musical theater. Since the early 1950s, she has appeared as a soloist in venues throughout Los Angeles, San Francisco, New York City, Mexico City, Madrid, Paris, London, Liverpool, and Valletta.
Beyond pure flamenco, Inesita's body of work includes The Mystery of Flamenco, a lecture-demonstration written by her husband, Bob Dworkin. Inesita lectured while demonstrating discrete parts of flamenco dance to illustrate structure, which she mostly performed in K-12 schools, colleges, and universities in Southern California between 1963 and 1988. Inesita has also presented a program featuring a suite of dances entitled Themes from Goya, which reflected the various stages of the Spanish painter's life. Its premiere at the Wilshire Ebell Theatre in 1955 was followed by performances at the University of California, Los Angeles in 1957 and at the Ivar Theatre in 1958. Another part of her oeuvre includes dances to the harpsichord sonatas of Domenico Scarlatti, which she premiered at the Wilshire Ebell Theater in Los Angeles 1970.
Since 2012, Inesita has performed with her own company featuring other flamenco artists and expanded her scope to integrate the talents of her colleagues with her own vision of Spanish theater. These programs have been presented by the Alhambra Performing Arts Center.
Sources: "About Inesita – Flamenco Inesita." Accessed July 22, 2019. https://flamenco-inesita.com/about/. Inesita (n.d.) LinkedIn page. Accessed September 16, 2019. https://www.linkedin.com/in/inesita-inesita-5b19a246.
Scope and Contents
This collection is comprised of materials relating to each episode in Inesita's performing life, which includes correspondence, photographs, contracts, programs, posters, press clippings, scripts, notes, and other printed ephemera spanning eight decades of shows and engagements (1939-2018). Inesita's husband, Bob Dworkin acted as her agent, and, thus, a significant amount of the material is connected to his administration of Inesita's bookings, payment, and publicity as a flamenco dancer. Scripts of The Mystery of Flamenco, a lecture demonstration presented by Inesita and written by Bob Dworkin are also included.
The collection contains audio and audiovisual material, which includes eleven VHSes; two vinyl records of Inesita in Flamenco and Classic Spanish Dances; ten 1/4 inch audiotapes; two 1/2 inch videotapes; and one U-matic. Additionally, there is a small amount of digital material (eight DVDs and five CDs), which include various audio and video recordings of piano and dance performances, or fragments of dance shows; as well as photographs and text from Inesita's book A Dancer's Life.
A significant amount of Inesita's personal correspondence and memorabilia are also included, such as fan letters, union cards, her Lester Horton Lifetime Achievement Award (2010), and her first dance dress.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Materials from California shows and engagements, 1934-2018
Series 2: Materials from shows and engagements in other U.S. states, 1945-2012
Series 3: Materials from shows and engagements abroad, 1940-1962
Series 4: Correspondence, 1913-2012
Series 5: Additional materials, 1923-2018
Related Materials
Willy Stahl papers (PASC-M 244). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
"Meet the Author" interviews, photographs, and reference materials (LSC 1755). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA. Collection is currently unprocessed. Please contact Special Collections reference (spec-coll@library.ucla.edu) for more information.
Flamenco dancers -- California, Southern -- Archives.; Women dancers -- California, Southern -- Archives.; Inesita; Dworkin, Bob
- Series 1: Materials from California shows and engagements, 1934-2018
  Scope and Contents
  This series is comprised of letters, contracts, programs, flyers, small posters, press clippings, and other ephemera related to Inesita's one-woman shows in California, particularly in her home base of Los Angeles. This includes materials from early piano recitals and flamenco shows; her film work from the 1940s and 1950s; The Mystery of Flamenco lecture demonstrations at various venues; Themes from Goya presentations; and dance shows to the harpsichord sonatas of Domenico Scarlatti. This series also contains material from performances presented by the Alhambra Performing Arts Center with Inesita and her ensemble. Additionally, this series contains various audio and video recordings of performances or fragments of dance shows captured in nine VHSes; one U-matic; one 1/2 inch videotape; two 1/4 inch audiotapes; five DVDs; and one CD.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS PROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment will be required for viewing. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - Programs from early piano recitals at Pacific Institute of Music & Fine Art, 1934-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Early flamenco performances, 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2-6)
    Includes materials (programs, flyers, contracts, press clippings, and letters) related to Inesita's earliest one-woman shows and concerts throughout Southern California, including her first flamenco show at La Golondrina Café on Olvera Street in Los Angeles (1939). Other highlights include materials from Inesita's first major solo concert at the Municipal Concert Hall Long Beach (1943); ten month run as featured Spanish dancer in the musical, The New Meet the People (1944); and solo concert at the Wilshire Ebell Theatre (1949). A sheet entitled "Resumé of Performances" by Inesita is provided for more information about venues, producers, and dates.
  - Film appearances in Skyline Serenade, Here Come the Girls, and Footlight Varieties, 1941-1953 (Box 9, Folder 2, Box 12, Laptop Reading Room laptop)
    Includes black-and-white photographs (8 x 10 inches), posters, flyers, contracts, letters, and press releases related to three films in which Inesita was featured as a dancer: Skyline Serenade (1941), Footlight Varieties (1951) and Here Come the Girls (1953). In addition, there is one VHS and one DVD with 2.83 GB (one digital file) of video of Inesita dancing in Here Come the Girls.
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - Pan American Concerts tours, 1943-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    Primarily programs from five tours of concert revues with Pan American Concerts at various venues throughout California such as the Wilshire Ebell Theatre; Lobero Theatre; Marines' Memorial Theatre; Long Beach Municipal Auditorium; American Conservatory Theater's Geary Theater; Embassy Auditorium; Pasadena Shakespeare Club; and more.
  - Performances for various Southern California agencies and organizations, 1952-2002 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    Includes letters, programs, and flyers related to performances for various Southern California agencies and organizations, such as the Council of Mexican American Affairs; Los Angeles Central Library; Beverly Hills Public Library; Biblioteca del Pueblo de Lincoln Heights; California State Federation; and Lincoln Park Recreation Center, among others.
  - Premiere of Themes from Goya at Wilshire Ebell Theatre, 1955 October 23 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes programs, flyers, press clippings, and a script.
  - Solo dances at Turnabout Theatre, 1955 November-December (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes flyers, programs and clippings from the Los Angeles Times related to Inesita's performance of three dances, Andaluza Sentimental, Zapateado de Estampio, and Maria Salome.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1955-1969 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
    Includes mostly clippings from the Los Angeles Times with both reviews and advertisements of Inesita's shows in Southern California. Clippings from student newspapers, such as the University of California, Los Angeles' (UCLA) Daily Bruin, are also included.
  - Themes from Goya performances at UCLA, 1957 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    Includes programs, postcards, and Inesita's handwritten program notes from two presentations of Themes from Goya at UCLA's Royce Hall on July 19 and November 8, 1957.
  - Programs from Themes from Goya performance at Ivar Theatre, circa 1958 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Performances at K-12 schools, colleges, and universities, 1957-1988, bulk 1963-1979 (Box 3, Folder 1-7, Box 12)
    Primarily letters to Inesita or to Bob Dworkin on her behalf regarding both performances and workshops in K-12 schools, colleges, and universities across Southern California. Contracts, flyers, letters, press clippings, and photographs are also included. Some recurrent institutions include UCLA, UC Santa Barbara, UC Riverside, Oral Education Center of Southern California, Inc., Los Angeles Unified School District, Pomona College, Head Start Programs, Claremont Graduate University, Area 7 Alternative School, El Camino College, Office of Los Angeles County Superintendent of Schools, California Institute of Technology, Santa Monica College, and more. This also includes videos of performances at 75th Street School, Head Start Programs, and California State College captured in four VHSes, one 1/2 inch videotape, and one U-matic. Two 1/4 inch audiotapes of Inesita performing in 1965 at Caltech and in 1966 at San Fernando Valley State College are also included.
  - Programs from solo concert at Contemporary Dance Theatre, 1958 October 12-14 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Performance at Inner City Cultural Center, 1968 February 18 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes postcards, programs, flyers, press releases, and clippings.
  - Performance at Circle Star Theatre, 1969 February 17 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Includes postcards, programs, a contract, clippings, and letters between Bob Dworkin and representatives from the theater.
  - Premiere of dances to Domenico Scarlatti's sonatas at Wilshire Ebell Theatre, 1970 May 15 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    Includes programs, flyers, letters of praise to Inesita, handwritten notes, and newspaper clippings.
  - Video of performance at La Rosa, 2001 November 10 (Box 12)
    Includes one VHS with the label "Inesita Performance at La Rosa, Sat 10th Nov 2001, Tape #1."
  - Harpsichord Center Artist Concert Series concerts, 2001-2008 (Box 12, Box 13, Folder 8)
    Includes programs for various concerts from 2001 and 2008; as well as three VHSes from May 2001.
  - Flamenco shows presented by Alhambra Performing Arts Center, 2009-2017 (Box 4, Folder 3, Box 11, Folder 7, Box 12, Laptop Reading Room laptop)
    Includes photographs, flyers, programs, and press clippings of Inesita's flamenco shows presented by Alhambra Performing Arts Center (APAC). Inesita wrote on the back of each photograph with more details and information about the image. In addition, there are four DVDs with 14.2 GB (4 digital files) of video footage from 2009, 2010, and 2012; as well as one CD with 104 images (.jpg) of a performance in 2013.
  - Program and flyer from shows presented by Piano Forte Productions, 2010-2011 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Programs from shows at Havana Club Restaurant and Bar, 2014-2018 (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Series 2: Materials from shows and engagements in other U.S. states, 1945-2012
  This series is comprised of letters, contracts, programs, flyers, small posters, press clippings, photographs, and other ephemera related to Inesita's shows, tours, and The Mystery of Flamenco lecture-demonstrations throughout the United States. This includes one 1/4 inch audiotape recording of a lecture-demonstration at Springfield College in Springfield, Massachusetts; one VHS of performances in Las Vegas, Nevada; and one DVD of footage from a film about flamenco by New York University film students.
  - First show in New York City at the Havana-Madrid nightclub, 1945 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Includes programs, an autographed photograph and a letter from the comedian, Jerry Lewis (who was also in the production), and a letter from Inesita's friend and dancer, Nitza.
  - Programs from shows in Seattle, Washington and Kansas City, Missouri, 1945, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Includes programs from Inesita's concert revue at the Metropolitan Theatre in Seattle (circa 1945); and a production of Georges Bizet's opera, Carmen, at the Starlight Theater in Kansas City (1954).
  - New York City performances, 1953-1955 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
    Includes photographs, schedules, newspaper and magazine clippings, letters, contracts, press releases, programs, and flyers related to Inesita's performances in New York City. She performed at the Kaufmann Concert Hall at the 92nd Street Y, Asia Society and Museum, Isidor Straus Theatre of the Educational Alliance, and Nathaniel Macon Junior High School (J.H.S. 258), Central Needle Trades High School (presently High School of Fashion Industries), and the Brooklyn Academy of Music (BAM).
  - Photographs of Inesita in New York City, 1954-1962 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Includes black-and-white photographs (8 x 10 inches) of Inesita either posing in costume or performing.
  - Programs from performances at Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, 1954, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Summer tour with Pryor-Menz, 1955 February-July (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Contains materials from Inesita's five week tour under the auspices of Pryor-Menz Concert Service, which consisted of twenty-three concerts in colleges and universities in Texas, Kansas, Wyoming, Minnesota, and Illinois. Materials include letters to Bob Dworkin from Pryor-Menz about bookings, payment, and publicity. There are also press releases, contracts, letters of praise to Inesita, newspaper clippings, programs, and a detailed itinerary with information about her reservations and performances.
  - Virginia Symphony Orchestra performances, 1962-1969 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Primarily correspondence between Bob Dworkin and William Haaker, Musical Director of Virginia Symphony Orchestra, Family Concert Division regarding payment, publicity, and promotion of Inesita's performances in Covington, Virginia; Fairfield, Illinois; Anadarko, Oklahoma; Holdenville, Oklahoma; and Guymon, Oklahoma. Newspaper clippings from these performances, as well as photographs of Inesita and Bob at a social gathering in Covington, are also included.
  - New York University student film featuring Inesita, 1962-1963, 2010-2012 (Box 9, Folder 5, Laptop Reading Room laptop)
  - Springfield College performance, 1963 January 22 (Box 5, Folder 2, Box 12)
    Includes correspondence, programs, newspaper clippings, and one 1/4 inch audiotape recording from Inesita's lecture-demonstration, The Mystery of Flamenco, at Springfield College in Springfield, Massachusetts.
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - Video recording of performances and workshops in Las Vegas, Nevada, 2004 January 10 (Box 12)
    Includes one VHS with the label "Inesita (6) segments of performances Jan 10, 2004, Community College, Las Vegas, NV, Guest Artist, Fiesta Flamenca Dance Co."
- Series 3: Materials from shows and engagements abroad, 1940-1962
  This series is comprised of letters, contracts, programs, flyers, broadsides, press clippings, photographs, and other ephemera related to Inesita's performances in Malta, Spain, England, and France.
  - Mexico City performances, 1940 June, 1956 February 14 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
    Includes materials related to Inesita's performances in Mexico City at the Rio Rita Sala de Fiesta in June of 1940 and the Instituto Mexicano Norteamericano de Relaciones Culturales in 1956. This consists of contracts, programs, and clippings. There is also one photograph of the 1956 performance included.
  - Programs from a show in Managua, Nicaragua, 1950 May (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Press clippings about Inesita's performances in Spain, 1953-1959 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
  - Paris, France performances, 1959-1962 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Contains materials from Inesita's performances in Paris, France, such as correspondence between Bob Dworkin and French cultural agencies regarding potential bookings, programs, posters, newspaper magazine clippings, and press releases. Inesita performed at Le Catalan restaurant and the American Center for Students and Artists (presently the Foundation for Arts Initiatives).
  - Photographs of Inesita performing in Paris, France, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Includes black and white photographs (8 x 10 inches) by photographer, Roger Denizon, of Inesita dancing flamenco with Pedro de Linares and Eduardo Martinez on guitar at Le Catalan restaurant. Inesita wrote on the back of some photographs with more details and information about the image.
  - England performances, 1960-1962 (Box 5, Folder 6-7, Box 6, Folder 1-3)
    Includes materials related to Inesita's performances throughout England, such as correspondence between Bob Dworkin and venue directors, programs, newspaper and magazine clippings, press releases, photographs, flyers, scripts, handwritten notes, and other ephemera. While in London, Inesita performed at Morley College, London University, London College of Education Dance, St. Pancras Town Hall (presently Camden Town Hall), and at Victoria Halls for the Imperial Society of Teachers of Dancing. She performed at the Crane Theatre (presently Epstein Theatre) in Liverpool and at Birmingham University.
  - Photographs of Inesita in London, England, 1960-1962 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Includes black and white photographs (8 x 10 inches) of Inesita either posing in costume or performing in London. Also includes one photograph of the Maharajah of Mysore being presented to Inesita as patron of her first concert in England. Inesita wrote on the back of each photograph with more details and information about the image.
  - Manoel Theatre in Valletta, Malta performances, 1961 October (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Includes materials related to Inesita's performances at the Manoel Theatre in Valletta, Malta, such as correspondence between Bob Dworkin and Captain Paul Bugeja and others from the Malta Government Tourist Board regarding payment, publicity, and promotion of the engagement. This also includes programs, clippings, and a poster.
  - Photographs of Inesita and her ensemble in Valletta, Malta, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    Includes black and white photographs (8 x 10 inches) captured by the Malta Government Tourist Board of Inesita in Valletta, Malta with her ensemble: guitarist, Paco Torres; pianist, John Vernon; and singer, Juan Martin ("Manolette"). Includes mostly photographs of Inesita in Spanish dance poses (bolero, muiñeira, and flamenco) at the Manoel Theatre, the Palace of the Baron of Marquise Luchona, the Ħal Saflieni Hypogeum, and the Tombs of Malta. Inesita wrote on the back of each photograph with more details and information about the image.
- Series 4: Correspondence, 1913-2012
  This series is primarily comprised of Inesita's personal correspondence with friends and dance partners throughout the years. This includes a small amount of letters written to Inesita's father, Willy Stahl as well as letters to Inesita from her mother, Minnie Stahl. Greeting cards sent to both Inesita and Bob Dworkin are also included.
  - Early letters to Inesita and her family, 1913-1939 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Includes a letter written in German to Inesita's father, Willy Stahl; two letters to Inesita from her mother, Minnie Stahl; a card celebrating Inesita's nineteenth birthday from Helen; and a postcard from Minnie to Willy.
  - Letters to Inesita from Antonio Triana, 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Olga J. Rosenthal and Lynden Behymer, 1940-1945 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Inesita from Oscar Tarriba, 1941-1942 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Inesita from Carlos Montoya, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Includes some letters that are written by Montoya's wife, Sally Montoya, on his behalf.
  - Greeting cards to Inesita and Bob Dworkin from friends and fans, 1949-2006 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Letters between Bob Dworkin and various people, 1951-1986 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Primarily letters from Bob Dworkin to performing arts organizations, newspapers, politicians and others regarding Inesita's show bookings and publicity.